Hey, it's Hi, noon and old Cheyenne. I'd
like to call the June 16th meeting of
the finance committee to order. Uh, if
you have your cell phone with you, make
sure it's on vibrate or mute. When
making public comment, clearly identify
yourself. And online, use the raised
hand function. Our staff will let you
know when you can unmute yourself. Uh
following this uh agenda, there will be
no additional business discussed
and most importantly all communications
go through the chair. And with that cl
first item, please.
>> Number 13, ordinance third reading,
defining the terms and conditions of
employment for sworn officers of the
Cheyenne Police Department for July 2026
until the end of fiscal year 2027.
>> Staff report.
>> Mr. Mr. Chair, members of the committee,
Captain David Jane, Cheyenne Police
Department. What you have before you is
our terms and conditions for sworn
employment. This comes up every year
with with a new budget and it reflects
all the changes that were already
approved in the budget. And I stand for
any questions.
>> Any comments or questions from
committee?
>> Seeing none, we'll go to public comment
in the room.
No public comment in the room. Public
comment online.
No. Back to the committee. What's your
pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to approve on third
and final reading.
>> Second.
>> Moved by Councilman Moody, second by
Councilman Wolf. Any further discussion?
>> All in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that that is unanimous. The
recommendation of the finance committee
will be to approve at the next meeting
of the governing body. Next item
>> number 30. Resolution authorizing
submission of an application to the
Wyoming State Loan and Investment Board
for a loan from the Wyoming Drinking
Water State Revolving Fund for an amount
not to exceed $20 million for the lead
service line investigation and
replacement project and authorizing the
mayor, city clerk, and director of the
board of public utilities to execute the
application and all related documents.
>> Staff report. Welcome, gentlemen.
Good afternoon, uh, Mr. Chair and the
committee. Uh, my name is Bryce Biller.
I'm with the Cheyenne BOPU engineering
department. Um, and with me I've got
Jeff Foreman, uh, GIS supervisor BOP.
>> So, just a little background on um this
loan request. Um the EPA has established
uh rules that are pushing all public
water supply uh suppliers to uh identify
and ultimately remove all lead water
service lines from systems. Um on the
worst level, we foresee the potential of
upwards around $und00 million to
complete this overall project. Um, so
initially our plan was to take it off in
slow chunks. Um, and while we're doing
that, we found that the state land
investment board actually did have some
federal funding specifically for this
effort uh to where it was near um
expiration where that money would have
been reverted back to the federal
government. Um, so they highly
recommended that we apply for this. Uh,
one of the benefits to us and to our
rateayers is that there is the potential
for uh, 25% principal forgiveness. Uh,
so that's a pretty good chunk of change.
That's essentially no money to no cost
to our rate payers. So that's why we're
moving forward with um, this amount.
It's not uh the total that we'll
ultimately need to complete all the
replacements and everything, but we do
believe that it's enough to get us
through kind of the uh investigatory
phase going out doing a lot of
potholeing at private re residences and
identifying what uh material the service
lines are constructed of. Um and then
also having a little money there to um
replace any what we call high-risk
customers. Those would be like medical
facilities, child care, schools, that
type of thing. So, um, with that, that's
a little bit of background and we're
we're happy to answer any questions.
>> Any, uh, comments or questions from
committee? Councilman Moody.
>> Thank Mr. Chair through. Thank you,
gentlemen. Um, here at the, uh, bottom
of the resolution and for the public to
see, it's the very last one. Um, Paulo
investigation definitely understands
service line replacement. Absolutely
understand. What would be other
administrative costs? What would that
entail?
>> Uh Mr. Chair, through you. Uh
administrative costs can be anything
like uh pursuing uh permits. Uh we'll
have to uh have some right-of-way work
that potentially will happen. Uh we'd be
looking at potential uh flood plane
work. Um, an administrative cost is a
pretty standard
um term that would be included in any
sort of um construction type contract.
Uh there's things that potentially
unforeseen uh that could apply to that.
That could be traffic control, uh things
like that. There's lots of different um
components that don't fall under those
specific uh potholeing or replacement
activities.
follow up.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Thank Thank you
very much for the answers. It's just so
that way the public knows what's going
on. Thank you.
>> Absolutely,
>> Councilman Wolf. Um Mr. Chairman, uh
thank you very much. Um through you. Um
thank you, Mr. Door. And um I'm I mean
this this is um terrific on its face. Um
and um do do you have people who are
basically assigned to a team that's
actually doing the the investigative
work um on these projects?
>> Yeah. Um we've established a team of uh
kind of all hands on deck at the BOPU.
Uh specifically, our GIS department is
handling um the project management of
um identifying high-risisk service
lines, classifying them into categories.
So, we're focusing on a a high-risk area
first,
um doing highintensive investigations in
those areas of every service line
because uh lead was installed
sporadically
>> throughout those areas. And then we
intend to get into kind of a buffer area
to where uh EPA will allow us to do uh
statistical sampling. So 95% confidence
interval throughout the rest of the
areas of the city. Um we've hired one
full-time
um construction inspector. He's now
going through QAQC on every single
service line. We have to link each
service line to a customer in our system
so that every customer is accounted for
through a service line. Um and then with
that it'll be released to Bryce and his
team uh to put together hydro excavation
contracts that they will then go out
hydro excavate them uh complete
inventories while they're they will
gather photo evidence um and then it
will be documented for submission
through a baseline inventory to the EPA.
Um we've also put together um our
existing PR team is working on um
outreach to the public responding to
annual notifications
um outreach when we begin to do
investigations.
Um our water treatment division is
handling the sampling side of the entire
process. Um when this goes live in 2027,
November 2027,
um when you discover lead, you have to
provide a filter picture to anyone with
lead. There's another category called uh
galvanized requiring replacement, which
is you can't prove that one half
upstream uh was never lead. If the
downstream is galvanized, then it's
considered it could hold lead particles
and we have to have additional outreach.
um for sampling for um filter pictures
on both lead and GRR.
>> Um so yeah, hopefully that answers your
question. We we've um really not hired
additional staff other than one person
and we've kind of taken the approach of
um use personnel that we have to take a
lean approach to um using our rateayers
money the best
um the best way we can.
>> Follow up.
>> Yes. Um, thank you, Mr. Chairman,
through you. Um, well, I I really
appreciate the explanation. Um, thank
you very much. Um, we get criticism from
at least one person almost all the time
that we're not doing enough on this and
um, it's great to see that, you know,
we're um, we're moving ahead with this
and uh, significant uh, investment in
it. Um, anytime you can get free money
and then maybe some loan forgiveness,
that's a that's a pretty good deal for
the the city and the BOPU. Um,
Mr. Doro, what what do you have to
reapply for this money uh annually or
just submit reports and and it will
continue in effect?
>> Yeah, Mr. Chairman, through you. So th
this is typical to really any slid loan
where um we are approved up to a certain
amount. Uh that final number will be
approved through the state land
investment board. Um and from that point
we are uh qualified to spend up to that
number. Um the way it'll work is we will
essentially submit um monthly uh
reimbursement requests through SLIB. Uh
depending on how much work was done that
that month, they would then reimburse
the BOPU that amount. Um and then uh at
the completion of the project when all
of the money is spent andor the project
is complete um then that's what kind of
kicks off the um loan portion of it. Uh
in this situation it's a 0% interest. So
there's not a whole lot of um timing
that necessarily goes into that in terms
of the portion that we would have to pay
back. But we would uh between now and
then continue to do what we had planned
from the beginning where we're budgeting
a certain amount every month or every
fiscal year um to make sure that we are
set up and spreading those costs over a
longer period of time uh to help control
some of those um you know big uh rate
increases and that type of thing. Try to
try to control the costs for our rate
payers as much as we can.
follow up at all. Councilman Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Turn through. Um, just a
quick question just so that way the
public knows. Um, I'm assuming it will
most likely pass next Monday's city
council meeting. What's the earliest
this will be heard by the SLIB board?
Earliest possible month.
>> I believe that that is uh September um
is when they would have that that
meeting. Um if if my memory serves me
correct. Yeah.
>> Thank you. Councilman White, do you have
any questions?
>> I do not. Thank you, Mr. Chair.
>> Uh, I had one. So, I'm assuming uh a lot
of the other communities and why we will
be applying as well.
>> Um, Mr. chair. Um, essentially what we
have heard from SLIB is that there are a
few communities that have um, applied
for this funding. Uh, there is one
program that they're running to where
they kind of have a a statewide
consultant that's helping some of the
smaller communities. Uh we've seen uh a
lot of communities are going out to
where they have just a limited number of
um potential lead service lines where
they are purchasing their own hydro
excavation truck um and then going out
and doing all this work um themselves.
Uh we did evaluate that uh in terms of
what that would mean for the board.
that's essentially buying a truck, uh
probably a whole another crew and having
them full-time on this. And just in
terms of the uh wear and tear on that
equipment um the additional resources
that would go into managing all of that,
we just felt that uh going the
consulting route um or the contractual
route uh was a a more
beneficial approach for the BOP in terms
of how many additional resources we
would need to to push towards this
effort.
And then once you've identified a
residential service line and the
occupants are notified or the
homeowners,
how much of of this expense will fall
back on the homeowner?
>> Uh so Mr. Chair, um in Cheyenne, uh we
are considered what's called a split
utility. Uh that essentially means that
half of the service line is publicly
owned by the BOPU and half of the
service line is owned by the private
land owner whether that's a business or
a homeowner or whatever the situation
is. So essentially the way that we would
foresee that going is if it if we
identify a service line at one of our
high-risk uh customers like we discussed
earlier that would be a situation where
we would um replace that immediately. Um
if it was not there's going to be a lot
of them. They will have to go into more
of a programmatic approach. Um, and what
we would do at that point is we would
budget to replace our half. We would
tell the property owner the situation
that they're in. Uh, we would educate
them with the potential risks. Uh, the
actions that they can take to protect
themselves in the interim while that's
there. Um, and as Mr. Fore foreman
mentioned earlier, we would provide them
with a um qualified lead filtering
pitcher um and a single filter unit um
to kind of get them kickarted, show them
what they're looking for. And then any
future filters that they would need or
want to use um in that situation would
be on their um decision uh to continue
to use those or not. Um, and then they
they would be it would be their decision
on whether they would want to replace
their portion of the service line when
we're in there or not. Um, if somebody
said we want to get this out of here
right away, we would put them in a
priority where we would do our half um
earlier and that would move up in terms
of the plan of of order of of when
things would be replaced. So, um, in
terms of the things that we would be
doing and requiring, there would be no
cost to the homeowner, they would have
some potential, um, personal decisions
on whether they would want to put the
money towards replacing their half of
that service line, continuing to use the
lead filtering pitcher. Um, anything I
missed there?
>> Yeah, I can add to that, Mr. Chair. Um
EPA has some strict guidelines on um
they call it under control. Um so what
portion of the service line is under the
utilities control and in the state of
Wyoming and the BOP specs we don't have
authorization past the curb stop
according to our ordinance. And so
what's under our control is just our
side of the curb stop as well as the
meter inside of the home. And if we
cross that boundary, we run into issues
with the EPA and the regulation. Um,
currently this is in um I believe
federal circuit court right now. Uh, the
American Waterworks Association has
filed a um a suit against the federal
government. It's um actively being
resolved because we aren't the only
utility that falls into this category.
uh and many utilities throughout the
United States are are running into this
problem to where um if we were to step
over that boundary and um use rateayer
money or public funds to replace that um
we would place the the entire utility in
a situation to where we then are in
under control of that service line and
we would almost take ownership of it
which would dramatically increase rates.
And so that's something that we're very
cognizant of and we've designed this
program uh around that. We've also uh
are working on a customer coordination
plan that anytime a lead service line is
replaced 45 days in advance, we uh need
to make contact for attempts to uh
coordinate with that homeowner to work
with them to replace it. Um we're
discussing ideas to where maybe during a
real estate transaction the replacement
of that service line could be um worked
into the rep into the cost of the the
transaction. Uh as well as um all
service lines must be replaced by 2037.
Um, but if they are not under your
control, they just have to be on an
inventory list noting that they need to
be replaced and we're working with that
homeowner to do so. And so we we've got
some some leeway there, but everything
under our control um needs to be
replaced by 2037. I'll just add that in
Cheyenne the split utility or the split
ownership um we've noticed or observed
that primarily lead is found between the
main and the curb stop. We typically
have not uh we have no recorded
incidents of lead beyond the curb stop.
That's still up in the air. We may
discover that upon investigation, but as
as of this date, um we know that it
mostly lies between the main and the
curb stop.
Uh my followup would be then if we can't
use public funds to create a program for
homeowners to apply for
a lowinterest loan or
even u
other funding options since we're a
government. We we can't use public funds
at all for that.
Um that's kind of what the lawsuit will
will give us further guidance on when
that resolution is found. Um the benefit
of having just lead on our side is that
um the only issue is if there's
galvanized on the customer side.
>> So we will keep that in our inventory.
Um we can offer mitigation strategies to
help the homeowner flush their lines. um
clean out airators, um have their water
tested with a a certified laboratory.
Um we intend to release all of our
findings from sampling
um that indicates lead concentration at
the tap. Uh and we will continue to
encourage our customers to follow those
procedures. Um, for the most part, we've
had um known lead service lines, as long
as they're being maintained
appropriately
test below the uh exceedence threshold,
uh, in 2027, that exceedence threshold
lowers. And so, we'll continue to
monitor that. So, our our our plan right
now is until uh the lawsuit pans out
between the federal government and AWWA,
um we're just trying to respond
accordingly
um based on that outcome.
>> Okay. U Thank you. Just I guess just
keep us posted on how that lawsuit's
progressing. Um any other comments or
questions from committee?
And we'll go to public comment in the
room on this item.
Seeing none public comment online.
>> No public comment online.
Okay. Come back to the committee. What's
your pleasure?
>> Chairman, I move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> Been moved by Councilman Moody, second
by Councilman Wolf. Any further comments
or questions?
All in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that that motion is unanimous,
the recommendation of the finance
committee to the next meeting of the
governing body will be to adopt. Next
item
>> number 31. Resolution authorizing the
submission of a transportation
alternatives program grant application
for the Persing Boulevard and Windmill
Road intersection project.
>> Staff report.
Good afternoon, Mr. Chair and members of
the committee. I'm Elizabeth Finiko, the
economic resource administrator for the
city of Cheyenne. Before you today is a
resolution authorizing the submission of
an application to the Wyoming Department
of Transportation for a federal
transportation alternatives program
grant for the Purging Boulevard and
Windmill Road intersection project. This
project will be located at Persing
Boulevard and Windmill Road near East
High School and focus on providing
muchneeded safety upgrades to the
intersection, including redesign of the
roadway for better traffic flow, traffic
signal upgrades, and new ADA components
to improve pedestrian safety. If the
city of Cheyenne is graciously awarded
this grant, the Federal Transportation
Administration via Y DOT will provide
$868,000
in funding support for this project. The
remaining balance of $91,222
will come from fifth penny sales tax.
This application was previously approved
by the Cheyenne City Council in 2025,
but was unfortunately not awarded any
funding by WOD. The city of Cheyenne
engineers office and the grants office
have been working closely together to
approve the original application and
gather letters of support for the
project. And with that, I stand for any
questions.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Yep. Hey, Mr. Chairman. Threeu. Thank
you, ma'am. Uh, when you say redesign of
the roadway, could you elaborate more on
that, please?
>> Uh, Mr. Chairman, through you to
Councilman Moody. My understanding is
the roadway they're looking at possibly
um extending the left turn lane so
traffic flows better out of East High
School and move the existing pedestrian
crossing from
if I am correct it's the south
intersection. Um currently there's two
pedestrian crossings. They're going to
eliminate one so that there's only one
point where traffic will encounter the
pedestrians and eliminate the likelihood
of collisions with pedestrians in that
intersection.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> It probably be the west one then cuz the
east one is closer to the school.
Yeah, Councilman Wolf.
>> Um, thank you, Mr. Chairman, through
you. Um, thank you for doing this. Um I
mean I think this is a wonderful project
and I really appreciate you resurrecting
it.
>> Um I I just had um it it says in in the
last whereas clause that um you're
funded on a reimbursement basis. So do
we have to advance essentially the
entire amount of the funding and then
bill them and then they pay us um for
that? Is that is that what that's saying
or something else?
>> Mr. chairman through you to councilman
Wolf. Typically with the TAP grant you
we will get build by the contractors. We
pay those bills out and then we bill Y
dot and Y dot will reimburse us with
those funds as we go along. So as the
project continues, we'll continue to
bill and get repaid.
>> Councilman White, you have any questions
on this item?
>> Um
no, not really, Mr. chair, but I would
just say um and obviously our colleague
from W 3 probably knows better than I,
but boy, this intersection has needed
safety upgrades and redesign for many
years. So, anything that can be done to
help improve
uh that intersection will be a big big
addition to uh safety in the community.
>> Absolutely. Uh, and we'll go to public
comment in the room on this item.
Any public comment in the room?
Public comment online.
Any public comment online?
Seeing none, we'll come back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to adopt.
>> Second. It's
>> been moved by Councilman Moody. Second
by Councilman Wolf. Any further
comments?
>> Councilman Moody. I think it was turning
through you. I'm glad my colleague from
Ward One brought that up online. Um this
is definitely one of the safety aspects.
So glad this is moving forward. That can
be pretty dangerous. Thank you.
>> Okay. All in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that that vote is unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee,
the next meeting of the governing body
will be to adopt. Next item,
>> number 32, resolution authorizing the
acceptance of a donation from Tallg
Grass ILS Holdings LLC for affordable
housing purposes and authorizing the
mayor to execute a donation agreement.
>> Steph,
>> good afternoon, Councilman Chair or
committee chair and Cheyenne members of
the committee. Elizabeth Finneo,
economic resource administrator for the
city of Cheyenne.
This resolution authorizes the
acceptance of a donation from Tallgrass
ILS Holdings LLC in the amount of
$2,900,000
for affordable housing purposes and
authorizing the mayor to execute a
donation agreement. The city shall use
the donation to fund, support, or
facilitate affordable housing components
of affordable housing projects within
the city of Cheyenne, including land
acquisition, public infrastructure
improvements, site preparation,
financing gaps, construction related
costs, and other costs necessary to
enable con the construction,
preservation, or operation of the
affordable housing units. Donation funds
may be used for shared or common
improvements within a mixed income
project only to the extent such
improvements support or are reasonably
necessary for the affordable housing
components of the project. And I stand
for any questions,
>> comments or questions on this item from
the committee.
>> None. Okay, we'll go to public comment
in the room.
Any public comment in the room?
Seeing none, public comment online.
Any public comment online?
Seeing none, come back to the committee.
What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> Been moved by Councilman Wolf, second by
Councilman White. Any further
discussion?
All in favor? Signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Any opposed?
>> No.
The the recommendation of the finance
committee will be to adopt at the next
meeting of the governing body with
Councilman Moody voting no. Next item
>> number 41 C minimum revenue guaranteed
payment agreement between the city of
Cheyenne and the air air service focus
team craft for fiscal year ending June
30th 2027.
>> Staff report.
>> Good afternoon. Brenda Maro, deputy city
treasurer. Before you today is the
annual contract between the Cheyenne
regional air service focus team and the
city of Cheyenne. This is a renewal of
the minimum revenue guarantee similar to
prior years approved in the sixth penny
2021. The amount of the contract for
FY2027 is 380,9280
and we have a representative available
for questions as well as myself.
I'm answer questions from the committee
for Miss Maro.
I see none. Public comment.
Miss Vulk. Welcome.
>> Public comment. Wendy Vul with Shyen
Regional Air Focus Team Volunteer uh
president of an organization that was
formed in 2017. You'll recall in 2018 is
when Cheyenne lost um air service and we
are so indebted to the collaborative
effort with our Wyoming Department of
Transportation Aeronautics Division and
the city and the county and the number
of participants that have helped in
terms of supporting a minimum revenue
guarantee. The agreement before you is
what the voters had approved as a six
penny project funding going toward a
minimum revenue guarantee and we are
seeing right now in terms of the
participation is for this next year is
the state of Wyoming contributes 60% of
that minimum revenue guarantee guarantee
before you is the city's portion that's
20% and then the county commissioners is
the other 20%. So locally, the city and
county combined um together contribute
40% of that minimum revenue guarantee
and the 60% is at a statewide level. We
are now at since the new terminal opened
and air service resumed in November of
2018. We've had over 250,000 passengers
fly in and out of the new terminal. And
that's given the fact that we also had
three runway shutdowns, an unprecedented
pandemic, uh, shut down air service
nationwide. And so despite some
challenging headwinds, we are seeing
that the load factor, which means of the
seats that are available to sell and to
fill, we're at about 86%.
So that's pretty remarkable from going
from ground zero of having no air
service to now having our community
embrace it. It's a 17-minute flight
typically in the air and you spend more
time on the tarmac waiting to depart
from Cheyenne or to be able to um get to
a gate in Denver. So, we're pleased with
that United Express service we have. The
partners with Sky West and I'd be happy
to answer any questions.
>> Any comments or questions from the
committee for Miss V?
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh Mr. Chairman, thank you through you.
Um,
I've used the service a number of times
just recently. Um, and um, that's worked
great. Uh, I I really want to thank you,
Miss Folk, for um, all the work that you
put into this for a decade now or more.
Um, it's um, it's it's been a really
challenging effort. Um, but it looks
like it's paying off now dramatically.
um is what's your sense of the
legislaturator's support to continue
their 60% cost share?
>> Mr. Chairman through you to Councilman
Wolf. Um what we're we're really because
of our relationship that we've had a
strong working relationship with the
Wyoming Department of Transportation
Aeronautics, we were able to be a part
of the statewide capacity purchase
agreement. So that gives us, you know,
quite a bit of reassurance that by being
under that umbrella of those dedicated
funds that the state of Wyoming was to
negotiate with Sky West a much larger I
I would call it a purchasing power for
us to be a part of that. So we get a
quarterly invoice from the airline. The
state of Wyoming reviews it, Craft
reviews it, the Cheyenne airport even
reviews it to make sure of um accuracy.
And then on a quarterly basis, then we
give back an invoice to the city. Um,
and that statewide capacity purchase
agreement. What I've had to do on an
individual year-by-year basis is Craft
and Sky West have to enter into a
memorandum of understanding. Um, first
Sky West and Craft have to enter into an
actual MRG agreement and then I have to
come to the city and the county to get
memorandum of understanding for the
local participation. With the statewide
capacity purchase agreement, it's then a
three to fouryear commitment. So, it
helps in terms of us getting, I think, a
better purchasing power and at a
commitment level that we were not able
to do as a standalone year-by-year
basis.
I have a followup on that. Um, Miss V,
do you have any idea how many other
airports in Wyoming take advantage of
that state funding?
>> I do. U, Mr. Chairman, um, and again,
I'm not an expert in terms of why do,
but I believe like Gillette has just
come off of the minimum revenue
guarantee, and that's our ultimate goal
is to transition Cheyenne off of a
minimum revenue guarantee and be able to
have, you know, an airline flying here
directly. But Gillette because of it
being embraced in terms of the
writership if you will on the that route
from Denver to Gillette has been very
strong. But there's communities such as
um
the middle of the state um Cody Cody's
on minimum revenue guarantee. Then we
have also um Rock Springs. We have um
Laramie Casper's off of that um Sheridan
is on that. So again they fortunately is
when you get to a certain level then the
airline will see um that it's and we are
on the cusp in my opinion of really
getting to where we can be you know an
airline would fly here at risk again.
>> Good.
Um, you have any questions, Councilman
White?
>> I don't, Mr. Chair. Just what Miss Bulk
said in that if we didn't have this and
if the voters didn't overwhelmingly
um approve this on the six penny ballot,
um, air service from our community would
be
practically non-existent. So the fact
that the community recognized the
importance of this and that we and the
county have both consistently supported
this over the years has brought us to
the point what that Miss Bulk said that
we are really on the cusp now because of
of just the increased uh wrership
um to coming off the MRG and and I think
that will be a victory for everybody.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Okay, we'll go to
public comment in the room on this item
or any further public comment.
Any public comment online?
Okay, come back to the committee. What's
your pleasure?
>> Uh, Mr. Chairman, I move to approve an
amount not to exceed $380,928.80.
>> Second.
>> Been moved by Councilman W, second by
Councilman White. Any further
discussion?
All those in favor signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Seeing that that vote is unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to approve. Next item
>> number 41D, Industrial and Economic
Development Services Agreement between
the city of Cheyenne and the Cheyenne
Larmy County Corporation for Economic
Development known as leads for the
period of July 1st, 2026 to June 30th of
2027.
>> Steph,
>> good afternoon. Brendan Mow, Deputy City
Treasurer. Before you today is the
annual economic development contract
between Leeds and the city of Cheyenne
for the period of July 1st, 2026 to June
30th, 2027. The contract amount is
$100,000 and was included in the
recently approved fiscal year 2027
budget. Um Relle from Leeds is attending
today if you have any specific
questions. And I'm also available for
questions. Any comments or questions
from the committee for either deputy
treasure or representative from leads?
Councilman Wolf. Mr. Chairman, thank you
for you. Um,
thank you very much for what you do for
us, Brenda, to keep an eye on all of
this. Do we pay this as a lump sum? I
That's what I read in the contract that
it sounded like we by the end of the
year or
>> Yes, we pay annually. Okay. one check.
>> Great. All right. Um, thank you. Thank
you, Mr. Chairman.
Councilman White, you have any comments
or questions on this item?
>> I do not.
>> Okay, we'll go to public comment in the
room.
Any public comment in the room? Public
comment online.
No public comment online.
Okay, back to the committee. What's your
pleasure?
>> Uh, Mr. Chairman, I move to approve and
amount nitro seed $100,000.
>> Second.
>> Been moved by Councilman Wolf, second by
Councilman Moody. Any further comments
or questions?
All in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that, that vote is unanimous. The
recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to approve. Next item,
>> number 41E, a memorandum of
understanding between the city of
Cheyenne and the Cheyenne Downtown
Development Authority for the fiscal
year beginning July 1st, 2026 and ending
June 30th, 2027.
>> Staff report.
>> Good afternoon. Uh Sophia Maize,
executive director of the DDA for the
record. The item before you is renewal
of the work program between the city and
the DDA which is allow allowable under
city code 2.76.060.
Thisou would continue this to allow the
city to provide professional and
administrative services to the DDA board
for the purposes of administration of
redevelopment programs and efforts in
the downtown development district.
Thisou reflects the planning and
development department's portion of the
city's fiscal year 2027 uh budget which
was approved on June 8th, 2026.
Thisou is similar to the fiscal year
2026 agreement in that the DDA board
will continue to be staffed by the city
via the planning and development
department. The DDA executive director
will serve as the primary contact for
the DDA. The board of directors will
hire employees to implement the board's
vision as set in adopted plans and DDA
staff members will be city employees
with city benefits but will only act
under the authority of the DDA board and
not under the the direction of the city
or any of its departments.
One key change from the previous
agreement is that the city treasurer's
department shall serve only in advisory
capacity uh providing guidance as needed
to ensure proper financial practices are
maintained. We are uh incredibly
grateful for the city treasurer support
thus far and um very grateful for their
continued support and advisory capacity.
To help um bridge this gap of accounting
uh assistance, the DDA will contract
with an external CPA uh the qualified
CPA with governmental assistance for
data day-to-day accounting and we'll
explore options for potentially more
internal support.
The benefit of this agreement is the
increased potential retention of DDA
staff by providing HR and payroll
services, legal services from the
municipal perspective from the city
attorney's office, and the city benefits
for full-time staff if they elect to do
so. By providing these personal costs,
approximately $280,000 of the DDA mill
levy becomes available to support
operations such as grant programs,
public improvement programs, and
sponsorship of community events. DDA as
city staff allows more over oversight
from the municipality to ensure
compliance with the regulating city
code, state statutes, and the state
constitution, which is critical for a
municipal board. While the DDA while the
DDA is stabilizing, the provision of
personnel and benefits allows staff to
focus on building and maintaining the
systems for for sustainable operations
and implementation to be a standalone
entity.
The DDA has been in and out of the
standalone structure in the past with
instability always typically returning.
The current current between the city and
the DDA ends on June 30th this year. The
renewal agreement before you is valid
for one fiscal year per the city code
and will need to be reconsidered prior
to expiration on June 30th next year. I
stand for questions.
>> I'm answered questions for the director,
Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chairman through you.
Um, Director Maize, I um
I strongly support what you're doing. I
want to thank you and your staff um who
are here today um for the uh really
amazing efforts that you're putting into
this. Um, I went down to the summer in
the streets and uh, I know that wasn't
your event, but um, it um, it was still
a wonderful thing to see and see all the
people there and and I got a incredibly
positive report from somebody who's been
one of uh, your uh, off and on critics
and um, so um, I think all that is is
great. Are are you still in the limbo on
the space issue? Um um thank you
Mr. Chair through you to Councilman
Wolf. Uh we are still looking at
potential locations. That hasn't been
the priority in the last month or so.
There's been some other um things that
the board has been focusing on. However,
we do have rent and office space
allocated in the mill levy budget if it
comes to that. And we do have um a
potential contact in a downtown office
that that we can look at and I plan to
potentially present in the next month or
so.
>> Followup.
>> No, thank you. I I really appreciated um
the weekly reports that you send us um
and um your staff's real careful
attention to that. Excited to see the
rail cars come down. Thank you for
grabbing a hold of the notion of getting
all of the that videotaped and are
videotaped. Man, am I is that an old
word?
But anyway, I I think um you know
there's a lot of exciting things going
down. Thank you for expanding the
district. Your work on that to bring in
new people is um very much appreciated.
>> Thank you, Councilman Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Turn through. Thank you,
Miss Mace. Uh, just a question. How many
uh current DDA staff are under the city
HR being paid? How many currently now?
>> Mr. Chair, through to through you to
Councilman Moody. Uh, currently we have
two full-time staff and one part-time
staff at 30 hours. Uh, the fiscal year
budget you council approved on June 8th.
Uh, we'll be shifting that part-time
person to full-time.
>> Oh, Mr. Chair, follow up. All right.
Thank you, Chair through you. And then
um just for the public to know it's on
this memorandum here for the $283,513
you say goals of DDA program. Uh what
what exactly are are you referring to
when with that uh particular uh sum of
money?
>> Mr. chair through you to council Moody.
The DDA in the last mill election 2023
there was no um no line item of
administrative costs for that mill levy
use. We we currently have around maybe a
little less than 500,000 that can be
used for administrative purposes. And so
if we can preserve that as long as
possible to continue administrative
costs that the city cannot cover and
instead utilize the city for personnel
and benefits, then we can um use that
283,000 instead for operations such as
our grant programs, um sponsorships,
things of that nature.
>> Thank you,
>> Councilman White.
>> Um I don't have any questions. I just
want to thank Sophia for the job that
she and her staff are doing. Um I think
the communication has improved greatly.
Um and I know that they will be uh
utilizing uh or they have some exciting
things coming up regarding uh that kind
of like the facade improvement grant uh
and the capital improvement grant. Um,
so I'll just uh tell my colleagues to
stay tuned on that because there's some
exciting things hopefully coming down
the pike for those both those.
Great. Okay, we'll go to public comment
in the room. Any public comment in the
room?
Public comment online.
Last call for public comment online.
Back to the committee with your
pleasure.
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to approve.
>> Second by Councilman Moody, second by
Councilman Wolf. Uh any further
discussion?
All those in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that that vote is unanimous. The
recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to approve. Next item.
>> Number 41F. agreement between the city
of Cheyenne and office of youth
alternatives and Laramie County School
District number one to provide crisis
response services
>> staff report.
>> Good afternoon, Chairman Escobel and
committee members. Jay Sullivan, the
director of youth alternatives. Um the
item before the committee this afternoon
is a uh relication of the contract that
we have with the Laram County School
District to provide crisis services. Uh
those crisis services include our
suicide and homicidal assessments and
response to uh the community needs um
when called upon by the district. Uh the
amount of this contract is $154,420
uh per year for a uh 2-year term and we
can renew at the end of that two years
for an additional 2-year uh term. Total
amount uh per year is like I said the
$300,854.
And I'll stand by for any questions.
>> Any questions for Mr. Sullivan from the
committee?
>> Just that he's literally upside down.
>> You know,
Chairman Escoel, I just noticed that and
I have no idea what is going on with the
uh the camera.
That is strange.
I think I have a glitch on my end.
>> You You've been in this business too
long, Jay.
>> I tell you what, I'm beginning to
wonder.
>> Well, all right. Well, we'll go to
public comment in the room.
Public comment in the room. Seeing none,
we'll go to public comment online.
Last call for public comment online.
Seeing none, come back to the committee.
What's your pleasure,
>> Mr. Chairman? Real quick, I just want to
make sure that on your recommended
action report, I did uh miss I put 64
and it should be 54. So, just so we get
the motion right. Thank you.
>> Uh Mr. Chairman, I move to approve
amount of $300,854.
>> Second. A been moved by Councilman
Moody, second by Councilman Wolf. Any
further comments or questions?
What's your With that? All those in
favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that that vote is unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to approve. Next item.
Number 42E contract modification number
one to contract number 8286 between the
city of Cheyenne and Matson Brandon LLC
for public defender services
>> staff report
>> from the chief of staff
>> chair throughu Amber Ash chief of staff
for this city before you for your
consideration today is a contract
modification um this modification will
take the monthly payment um to Madson
Brandon LLC from $4,500 $00 a month to
$7,500 a month for a total of $90,000
per year. Um, which is a difference of
$36,000.
Um, this will require a budget
appropriation from the general fund
reserves. It was not included in the
original budget. Um when we um when city
attorney Brody and I met with um Brandon
um the scope of work um has increased
and this contract reflects um that
increase in the scope of work um that we
are incurring in the municipal court
system. Um so um in addition the council
did approve hiring a parallegal um legal
assistant to support the public defender
as well. So um this is just part of the
triage to address the overall increase
in court services. And I'm happy to
answer any questions. I believe um
um Deputy Attorney Hopkinson is online
as well if we need him. and Councilman
Moody.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Three. Uh,
thank you, ma'am. U just curious, uh,
what formula was used to modify
increasing it by 36,000?
Like, what was that? What was the
formula used? What data was used?
>> Um, chair for through you, there wasn't
uh necessarily a formula per se. This
was a um discussion attorney Brody and I
had um with um Brandon to determine
um what was going to be required in
order to continue his services. Um and
so this was the negotiated rate that we
arrived at. Um I would note um for your
benefit that um the city currently has
one full-time public defender. Um, this
contract with Matson Brandon is a
quartertime contract. um without this
contract if there is a conflict or some
other sort of issue um in which our
public defender can't take it or um and
currently does not have the capacity
necessarily to continue to handle
additional cases um we would have to use
um we have a hourly attorney Crystal
Stewart who is um much more expensive on
a per hour basis um and so um really by
having a contracted attorney um to help
support us, it saves us both in terms of
not having to provide employee benefits
as well as ensuring that we have um
support for our public defender um since
we only have one full-time public
defender on staff.
>> Followup.
>> Yep. There's chairu. Thank you for the
answer, ma'am. What would be the hourly
rate for the other uh attorney?
um share through you for Crystal
Stewart. I need to double check, but I
want to say it's like $300 or dollars an
hour or something for her. I would need
to double check and I will get you that
information to confirm.
>> Great. Thank you.
>> Any further questions for chief of staff
from the committee?
Okay, we'll go to public comment in the
room.
Any public comment in the room on this
item?
Any public comment online?
Public comment online. Seeing none, come
back to the committee. What's your
pleasure?
Uh, Mr. Chairman, I um move to approve
an amount not to exceed
$36,000.
Um just noting that the original
contracts 54,000 and so we are
increasing that to $90,000 total. Second
for discussion.
>> Okay, it's been moved by
council second by councilman Moody.
Further discussion
>> right here.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you. I just need more
information with regards to this how
this was this number came about you know
rates from the other attorneys. saw us
all be a no vote. Thank you.
>> You know, we briefly discussed it during
the municipal court budget and uh
we we did realize that there was some
backlog that we needed to take care of.
So, um you'll get you some more
information before next Monday's
meeting. Uh with that, all in favor
signify by saying I.
>> I.
All oppose. No. Okay. The recommendation
of the finance committee at the next
meeting of the governing body will be to
approve with Councilman Moody voting no.
Next item
>> number 43 C. Consideration to purchase
between the city of Cheyenne and
America's Freedom Tribute for the
purchase of a Vietnam War Memorial Wall
for the Community Recreation and Events
Department.
>> Staff report. Uh Sam Payne, Community
Recreation Events. What you have in
front of you is a purchase agreement for
a replica of the Vietnam Memorial Wall.
This is a new wall which is 80% of the
original size. Um it will be located at
Freedom Point in Lions Park. Um
there this location lends itself well.
Uh we selected this location um as we
were approached by several groups that
were wanting to do individual projects
throughout the city. Uh we felt it best
that we combine everything all in one
location with room for expansion. Um we
have brought a traveling wall to this
location a couple of times if fits well.
Uh the location will be the west side of
the existing pathway. Um over you guys
all know where Freedom Point is, I'm
assuming. Um it's going to be the west
side of the existing path. It will be
illuminated. Um it's a highly visible
area. This area that we selected is
underutilized by the public. It is a
nice large open area, but it is
underutilized. Um
one other point it's it's going to
contribute to the water conservation um
efforts
the we are putting monuments in uh we
are going to go with a water-wise
landscape and we we will quite a bit of
uh blueg grass turf. Um with all the
talk of curtailment this will be this
will be some help. Um
the total price for this uh uh project
was $350,000.
Uh there was a down payment of $75,000.
Uh that was fundraised by the Veterans
Remembrance Memorial. Um this was a down
payment to go ahead and start the
fabrication of the wall. Uh the
remaining balance is what we're looking
at today. That was the $275,000.
Uh the mayor has approved one-time state
uh state distribution funds of $150,000.
Uh the remaining of the balance is
$125,000.
Uh that's going to come out of
enhancement funds. Any future donations
towards this uh this specific part of
the project or towards the project in
general um are will go back into the
enhancement funds. So we will recoup
funds. Um it is my understanding that
the governor has already committed to
contributing $100,000 for the wall. Um
so again, we will be recouping recouping
these funds. Um
we've already broken ground. We've been
kind of pecking away at it. We've worked
with uh local contractors quite a few.
They've been generous enough to do inind
donations or give us some uh product at
cost. And so I'd just like to mention a
couple of them. It's and there are more
uh legacy construction groups
five jacks to style surveying the
engineering. Um there are quite a few
groups that are excited about this
project as are we and I'll stand for any
questions. Any comments or questions
from the committee for staff? Councilman
Moody.
>> Thank you. Thank you, sir. I know we
talked beforehand. So again, future
plans to have like say a memorial for
the SpanishAmerican War because
unfortunately a lot of generations below
me. I'm a generation Xer don't remember
the same remember the name or and World
War I, World War II, Korean War, etc.
too. So there is room for those
particular wars, memorials.
>> Yes. Yes, sir. This is a a large area
and there is plenty of room for
expansion.
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you.
Um Mr. P, thank you for coming today. Um
tell us what's being built there now. I
walk by it most days. Um so we have in
the foreground closest to 8th Avenue.
understand that's going to be the
veterans
memorial and then behind it is this law
enforcement memorial.
So through you chair um uh the closest
to 8th Avenue is the uh war at home.
That's you're seeing the concrete path
right there. Uh there will be a panel
that was selected is cut out of metal.
Um it it will cast a shadow on the
ground. And this is for the 22 uh
veterans that take their lives every
day. Uh that's what that one is. Um the
wall runs along the west side currently.
And I forgot to mention this uh
currently closer to the pickle ball
courts. What you're seeing is um
building up to the compass uh the
compass of honor and there's going to be
the soldiers cross right there. uh along
those lines along one of the paths going
from pickle ball to it is uh from
there's there's a memorial for the war
on terror which was full and this is
what I forgot to mention was fully
funded by leadership uh Cheyenne and
that monument actually is being
delivered and installed today.
We have if you'd like to come up um or I
could email you renderings of this
project so you might have a better
visual.
>> Uh Mr. Chair want to follow up. Thank
you. Um
so Mr. Payne um deputy director so the
Vietnam wall uh you you poured a new
pathway
>> um which is quite handsome by the way.
So thank you for doing that. Um, and so
it's going to be on the western side of
that running up that big tree line. Is
that basically where it's located
through you, chair? Yes. Uh, it it will
only be offset off that new path about 4
foot is all and then you'll have lights
splashing up onto it. Four or five foot
uh somewhere along those lines. Uh, that
path was recently replaced. It used to
be, as I'm sure you're aware, uh an old
asphalt path that was uh needed
replaced.
>> Uh Mr. Chairman, a followup. Um when I
first heard about this project, I
actually was not very enthused about it
>> and Mr. Sanchez spent some time talking
to me about it. Um, I I guess I and your
your answer to Councilman Moody is
interesting because
I I guess this is just a personal
statement. I mean, this is a public park
used by lots and lots of people and um I
guess I worry a bit that we're going to
fill it up with lots of other memorials.
And I know Americans love memorials. Um,
this is nothing against the veterans. My
father was a career army officer and um
but
will there be any sort of public
processes involved in making decisions
about what other things might get built
there?
>> Uh through you chair there can be um you
know we haven't had any other groups
approach us currently. So our plan what
we have is our plan what we have right
now. Um we are open to future expansion.
Uh, I imagine if you would like to see
uh public input, public comments
regarding those, we absolutely could do
that.
>> Councilman White, do you have any
comments or questions?
>> Yes, I'll just make a a comment. I I I
love the project. Um, I really would
have preferred a different location. Uh,
one of one of our other parks, Romero,
specifically Romero or uh Holiday. Um so
I um I think that there needs to be some
public input uh when projects of this
size are um planned and and implemented
into our parks because I think all of
our well not all of them but some of our
parks are getting pretty full and you
know the reason why their park spaces is
that you provide some um some quiet open
spaces where folks can go and and just
uh you know there's there's the bustle
of a park which is the pickle ball
courts and and other areas but there's
also um opportunities for relaxation and
um I think the project is wonderful. Uh
I think it's going to be beautiful. Um,
I just wish that it would have been in a
location, but um, I lost out on that,
but I will go ahead and support the, uh,
the item today and at the next meeting.
>> Thank you. Um, Sam, so originally we
were going to get one of the
original traveling walls, correct?
>> Uh, Mr. Chair, that is correct. Uh we
had a uh it was the
uh it was I'm sorry the Veterans
Remembrance Memorial who was fundraising
for that. We were originally going to
get a used wall, a retired wall. Um that
the wall that was available, we decided
it was too damaged and so we decided to
move with a with fabrication of a new
wall.
Do you have any idea how many other
communities have replicas of the Vietnam
traveling law?
>> I don't, but I'm sure I could figure
that out for you and email that to you.
>> I don't I don't
>> I was just curious.
It be nice if we were like one of the
few. Okay. Uh we'll go to public comment
in the room.
Any public comment in the room on this
item?
Seeing none public comment online.
Any public comment online?
Had a lot better break today than
Councilman Woman Aldrich did yesterday,
didn't he?
Okay, we'll come back to the committee.
What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Mr. Chairman, I move to approve an
amount not to exceed $275,000.
>> Second.
>> Been moved by Councilman Moody, second
by Councilman White. Any further
comments? Councilman Moody.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through
you. Uh, thank you for that report. I
mean, I'm definitely support of this,
but again, I want to see more expansion.
I mean, I've seen the Spanish American
War Memorial in Arlington. It's in bad
shape. That's in Arlington. Arlington.
Wouldn't be nice to have one here.
World War II as well because
unfortunately a lot of our youth, they
don't know about it. I mean, if you go
to the World War II memorial, Washington
DC, there's people there, especially
during the spring, summer, and fall
months that are, you know, just relaxing
right there, you know, because it really
shows our victory there over the access.
So, you know, I would like to see other
memorials come about for other wars even
when Wyoming is still a territory. Thank
you.
Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh, Mr. Chairman, through you. Thank
you. Um,
I've been torn by this. All of the
discussion occurred before I was on the
council and so and to a certain extent.
Um, just to uh give some uh honor to the
people who've made this decision. I kind
of feel like Mr. White that the this is
a ship that sailed already. Um, I'm
going to vote no at the moment. Um, I'm
eminently persuadable. Um, and uh, I
want to go out there and take a closer
look at it and I and take you up uh,
Director Payne on um, to come look at
the renderings and see and um, so I'll
vote no for the moment, but um, we'll
consider that over the next week. Thank
you. Okay.
>> All in favor signify by saying I. I
>> I
>> opposed. No.
>> No.
>> Okay. Seeing that that as an affirmative
vote, the recommendation of the finance
committee at the next meeting in the
governing body will be to approve.
Seeing that we have no more items for
our committee
today, we are adjourned.
>> And madame chief of staff, I need to ask
you a couple questions.